# Cesar Augusto VALADES CRUZ, PhD

Nationality: French and Mexican Birthdate: 27/11/1985

SERPICO Team, Inria - Curie Institute, UMR144 CNRS. Email: cesar.valades@gmail.com

12 rue Lhomond, 75005 Paris, FRANCE Phone: +33 156246798

My research experience ranges from construction/running of advanced optical microscopes to processing/analyzing imaging data together with cell biology applications, as well as, machine learning, data handling, high-content imaging, and visualization of 3D+time data. Working experiences in different countries enable me to work independently and as part of international environments

### **PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE**

#### Postdoc/Engineer -Inria and startup Biotech Myriade

01/2021 - 12/2021

Project: Improvement of tracking and size estimation of virus and extracellular vesicles.

Collaboration between SERPICO Team and the Biotech startup Myriade. I develop mathematical models and image processing tools to improve the tracking and size estimation of virus and extracellular vesicles in their system VideoDrop.

<u>Inria Starting Research Position</u> – Team SERPICO Paris with Dr. C. Kervrann and Dr. J. Salamero, 04/2019 – 12/2020 French National Institute for Research in Digital Science and Technology (Inria) & CNRS-Institut Curie, Paris, France

Project: Acquisition, analysis, and visualization of 3D Dynamic cellular imaging of endocytosis/recycling mechanisms in the membrane during cell migration using machine learning.

I work in novel machine learning methods of image processing able to detect the main regions of interest, and automatic quantification of molecular interactions and cell processes. In addition, I collaborate in the development of machine learning-driven navigation and interaction techniques for 3D+Time data enabling the analysis of localized intra-cellular events (endocytosis and exocytosis) and cell processes (migration, division, etc.).

<u>Postdoctoral researcher</u> – Team of Prof. Ludger JOHANNES Curie Institute, Paris, France

01/2016 - 03/2019

Project: Advanced cellular imaging of endocytosis.

Development of 3D image processing and quantification methods to study different modes of endocytosis, using advanced high spatio-temporal resolution imaging and single particle tracking. In addition, I was also responsible of setting up a Lattice Light Sheet Microscope on the PICT-IBISA imaging facility at Curie Institute, which is part of the France BioImaging National Infrastructure.

<u>University Lecturer</u> Monterrey Institute of Technology and Higher Education, Mexico

01/2015 - 12/2015

Teaching Physics, mathematics, and differential equations.

# Research Engineer - CNRS Institut Fresnel, Marseille, France

12/2013 - 04/2014

Responsible of developing image processing and quantification methods for super-resolution microscopy (dSTORM).

# Ph. D with Dr. Sophie BRASSELET and Dr. Pablo LOZA-ALVAREZ

Institut Fresnel, Marseille, France & Institute of Photonic Sciences, Barcelona, Spain

12/2010 - 07/2014

Thesis: Polarized Super-Resolution Fluorescence Microscopy

Implementation of a novel method of super resolution microscopy, in combination with a polarized detection to study molecular orientation behaviors, to report structural information at the single molecule and at nanometric spatial scale.

#### **EDUCATION**

12/2010 – 07/2014	Erasmus Mundus PhD in Photonics Engineering, Nanophotonics and Biophotonics	
	Mentión Très honorable. Sobresaliente. Cum Laude.	
	Aix-Marseille University, France & Polytechnic University of Cat	talonia, Spain
08/2008 - 07/2010	Erasmus Mundus M. Sc. in Biophotonics for telecommunications and biotechnologies	
	GPA: 14.4/20 "Magna Cum Laude"	
	Ecole Normale Superieure de Cachan, France & Complutense University of Madrid, Spain	
08/2009 - 12/2011	MEng. in Quality Systems and Productivity.	GPA: 90.7/100
	Monterrey Institute of Technology and Higher Education, Mexic	co
08/2003 - 05/2008	B. S. in Mechatronics Engineering.	GPA: 92/100 "With honors"
	Monterrey Institute of Technology and Higher Education, Toluca, Mexico	

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

- [1] Vaz Rimoli, C.\*, Valades-Cruz, C. A.\*, Curcio, V., Mavrakis, M., Brasselet, S. 4polar-STORM polarized super-resolution imaging of actin filament organization in cells. Nature Communications (2022)
- [2] Prigent, S., Nguyen, H-N., Leconte, L., Valades-Cruz, C. A., Hajj, B., Salamero, J., Kervrann, C. SPITFIR(e): A supermaneuverable algorithm for restoring 2D-3D fluorescence images and videos, and background subtraction. bioRxiv (2022)
- [3] Prigent, S.\*, Valades-Cruz, C. A.\*, Leconte, L.\*, Maury, L., Salamero, J., Kervrann, C. BioImageIT: Open-source framework for integration of image data-management with analysis. bioRxiv (2021) [in Review].
- [4] Forrester A, Rathjen S, Garcia-Castillo MD, Bachert C, Couhert A, Tepshi L, Pichard S, Martinez J, Munier M, Sierocki R, Renard HF, Valades-Cruz CA, Dingli F, Loew D, Lamaze C, Cintrat JC, Linstedt A, Gillet D, Barbier J, Johannes L. Functional Dissection of the Retrograde Shiga Toxin Trafficking Inhibitor Retro-2, Nature Chemical Biology (2020)
- [5] Renard, H-F, Tyckaert, F., Lo Giudice, C., Hirsch, T., Valades-Cruz, C. A., Lemaigre, C., Shafaq-Zadah, M., Wunder, C., Wattiez, R., Johannes, L., van der Bruggen, P., Alsteens, D., Morsomme, P. Endophilin-A3 and Galectin-8 control the clathrin-independent endocytosis of CD166, Nature Communications (2020)
- [6] Briane V, Vimond M, Valades-Cruz CA, Salomon A, Wunder C, Kervrann C. A sequential algorithm to detect diffusion switching along intracellular particle trajectories, Bioinformatics (2020)
- [7] Salomon A., **Valades-Cruz C. A.**, Leconte L., Kervrann C. Dense Mapping of Intracellular Diffusion and Drift from Single-Particle Tracking Data Analysis, ICASSP 2020 2020 IEEE International Conference on Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP), Barcelona, Spain, 2020, pp. 966-970.
- [8] Torrino S, Shen W, Blouin C, Kailasam Mani S., Viaris de Lesegno C, Bost P, Grassard A, Köster D, **Valades-Cruz CA**, Chambon V, Johannes L, Pierobon P, Soumelis V, Coirault C, Vassilopoulos S, Lamaze C. EHD2 is a mechanotransducer connecting caveolae dynamics with gene transcription. J Cell Biol. (2018)
- [9] Banerjee A, Grazon C, Pons T, Bhatia D, Valades-Cruz CA, Johannes L, Krishnan Y, Dubertret B. A Novel Type of Quantum Dot– Transferrin Conjugate Using DNA Hybridization Mimics Intracellular Recycling of Endogenous Transferrin. Nanoscale (2018)
- [10] Shaban H\*, Valades-Cruz CA\*, Savatier J, Brasselet S. Polarized super-resolution structural imaging inside amyloid fibrils using Thioflavine T. Scientific Reports (2017)
- [11] Valades-Cruz CA\*, Shaban H\*, Kress A, Bertaux N, Monneret S, Mavrakis M, Savatier J, Brasselet S. Quantitative nanoscale imaging of orientational order in biological filaments by polarized superresolution microscopy. PNAS (2016)

#### **Reviews & comments**

[1] Johannes, L., Valades-Cruz, C. A. The final twist in endocytic membrane scission. Nature Cell Biology (2021) **Review assignments journals:** Bioinformatics, PLOS Computational Biology & Journal of Physical Chemistry Letters

#### **ADDITIONAL SKILLS**

**Computational Languages & Tools:** MATLAB, Python, C/C++, LabVIEW, Java, ImageJ/FIJI, Icy, IMARIS, GPU programming, Parallel computing, TensorFlow, Keras, Machine Learning, R, Prism, Microsoft Excel, Zen celldiscover, IDEAS(ImageStream) **Languages:** English, Spanish and French.

#### Ongoing PROJECTS & COLLABORATIONS

- 2019 Project NAVISCOPE: image-guided navigation and visualization of large data sets in live cell imaging and microscopy. INRIA IPL project, initiated to implement novel machine-learning methods able to detect the main regions of interest, and automatic quantification of sparse sets of molecular interactions and cell processes during navigation to save memory and computational resources.
- 2019 **Project BioImageIT: open-source integrator for Image DATA management and analysis.** Ongoing project of the Serpico TEAM in the frame of the NRI (National Research Infrastructure France BioImaging) and dissemination toward the 18 Imaging Facilities that constitute the Core of the Infrastructure.
- 2019 **Project: Ultrastructure imaging of actin assemblies imaged by polarized light sheet microscopy.** Ongoing collaboration in the frame of France Biolmaging R&D program for image processing of polarized light sheet microscopy data with Dr. Sophie Brasselet, Institut Fresnel.
- 2017 Project ANR: Data Assimilation and Lattice Light Sheet imaging for endocytosis/exocytosis pathway modeling in the whole cell (DALLISH). Collaboration to investigate endocytosis pathways in the whole cell using 3D single particle tracking.

# **Fellowships & distinctions**

2020-2022 Member of the Mexican National Research System (SNI 1) 2008-2010 Mexican National Council of Science and Technology (CONACyT) fellowship for Master 2010-2014 Erasmus Mundus Fellowship for PhD 2008-2010 Erasmus Mundus Fellowship for Master